Can the greatest romance of your life last only one night?
Before Sunrise is a drama, romance film directed by Richard Linklater.
An unexpected meeting on a train leads two travelers to
spend an evening wandering through Vienna.
As the night unfolds, they share stories and conversations about life and love, exploring new ideas
while a quiet intimacy grows between them, knowing it may be their only night together.
Jesse, played by Ethan Hawke.
Céline, played by Julie Delpy.
Wife on Train, played by Andrea Eckert.
Husband on Train, played by Hanno Pöschl.
Guy on Bridge, played by Karl Bruckschwaiger.
Guy on Bridge, played by Tex Rubinowitz.
Before Sunrise is a 1995 romantic drama film directed by Richard Linklater and co-written by
Linklater and Kim Krizan, and is the first installment in the Before trilogy.
In the film, Jesse (Ethan Hawke) and Céline (Julie Delpy) meet on a
train and disembark in Vienna to spend the night together.
Inspired by personal experiences, Linklater collaborated with Krizan, who previously appeared in his
films Slacker (1991) and Dazed and Confused (1993), to develop the film's screenplay.
Casting was extensive; it took nine months for Hawke and Delpy to be cast.
Principal photography took place in Vienna.
The plot is considered minimalistic, consisting mostly of
monologues and extended dialogue between the characters.
The film explores themes and differing perspectives on life, love,
time, death, self-discovery, and postmodern romance.
Before Sunrise premiered at the Sundance Film Festival on January 19, 1995, and
was theatrically released in the United States eight days later.
It grossed $22.5 million and received critical acclaim, particularly for its
screenplay, Linklater's direction, and acting performances.
Before Sunrise appeared on many critics' lists of
the greatest films of the year.
Retrospectively, the film received a rating of 100% on Rotten Tomatoes.
The sequel Before Sunset was released in 2004, and Before
Midnight, the third film, was released in 2013.
The film explores themes of talking, soulmates,
walking, austria, vienna, austria.
The tone is lighthearted and emotional.